CV & Supporting Statement

Pablo González-Suárez

Postdoctoral Researcher in Plant Development

E-mail p.gonzalez-suarez@leeds.ac.ukE-mail (alt.) pablidopsis@gmail.comLinkedIn linkedin.com/in/pablidopsisTwitter twitter.com/pablidopsis

I am a highly-motivated biologist with 5+ years of experience in plant sciences. I am a passionate and curiosity-driven researcher with a competitive publication track record in high impact academic journals, an excellent communicator, awarded with numerous honours and recognitions, and a mentor with experience in supervising students from different academic, social and cultural backgrounds.

Education

2019 – 2023 PhD Plant Sciences

University of Leeds, United Kingdom

 Thesis titled 'Environmental Regulation of End-of-flowering in Angiosperms'. Supervisor: Tom Bennett, University of Leeds.

2021 – 2023 MSc Biostatistics & Bioinformatics

Open University of Catalonia & University of Barcelona, Spain

- Achieved a Cum Laude recognition for the final year thesis.
- Thesis titled 'Mathematical Modeling of Cold Sensing in *Arabidopsis thaliana*'. Supervisor: Rea Antoniou-Kourounioti, University of Glasgow.

2018 – 2019 MSc Plant Biotechnology

University of Oviedo, Spain

• Thesis titled 'Strigolactones and Branching in *Pinus pinaster*'.

2014 – 2018 BSc Environmental Biology

Autonomous University of Barcelona, Spain

- Achieved 1st-class honours.
- Exchange student in BSc Biotechnology (University of Oviedo, Spain) during 2017-2018 as part of the SICUE Exchange Program.
- Thesis titled 'Arsenic and Plant Defence: A Holistic Vision'.

Research Experience

Sep 2023 – present

Research Technician in Cereal Development

University of Leeds, United Kingdom

• I research the temperature regulation of reproductive development in wheat (*Triticum aestivum*) using bioinformatics and molecular biology.

As part of the job, I work independently in two separate projects as well as
provide bioinformatic expertise to the rest of the group.

Feb - May 2023

MSc Research Trainee

University of Leeds, United Kingdom

- Short-term internship in which I carried out the bioinformatic analysis of an RNA-Sequencing dataset performed on wheat (*Triticum aestivum*).
- The main goal of the project was to characterize the effect of artificial heating on wheat reproductive development using systems biology.

May – Jul 2022

Turing Scheme Trainee

Centre for Plant Biotechnology and Genomics, Spain

• Placement fully funded by the competitive Turing scholarship, during which I trained on computational biology and mathematical modeling.

Jun - Sep 2019

Erasmus+ Summer Student

University of Leeds, United Kingdom

 Summer placement, fully funded by a competitive Erasmus+ scholarship, during which I assisted in a project aiming to characterise the evolution of a protein family in the plant kingdom using cloning and molecular biology.

Mar - Jun 2019

Intern

Regional Agri-food Research & Development Service, Spain

• I led a series of field trials in the Forestry Area, which involved monitoring plant growth and collecting and processing samples for hormonal analysis.

Oct - Dec 2016

BSc Research Trainee

Autonomous University of Barcelona, Spain

• I assisted with experimental work for a PhD thesis aiming to study the effect of zinc availability on the diversity of rhizosphere bacteria.

Jun – Sep 2016

Summer Intern

Atlantic Botanical Garden, Spain

• I was part of the Scientific Team of the garden, where my main task was the management of botanical collections, including the germplasm bank.

Other Professional Activities

Meeting Organization

2021 – 2022	Co-organizer IX International Symposium for Spanish Researchers in the UK Oxford, United Kingdom
2020 – 2021	Co-organizer and host 'Plantastic' Science Seminars Leeds, United Kingdom

Others

2019 – 2022 Plant Growth Suite Weekend Staff

University of Leeds, United Kingdom

Honors

2023	Best Poster Award, Genetics of Future Food Production and the Green
	Revolution 2.0, Genetics Society
2023	Best Talk Award, Faculty of Biological Sciences Postgraduate Researcher
	Symposium, University of Leeds
2022	Turing Scholarship, UK Government
2022	Junior Conference Grant, Genetics Society
2022	Travel Grant, Society of Spanish Researchers in the UK
2022	Grant for the Participation in the 'Communicating Your Science Workshop',
	Genetics Society
2022	Grant for the Participation in the 'Reverse Mentoring Project' , University of
	Leeds
2021	Best Poster Award, VIII International Symposium from the Society of Spanish
	Researchers in the UK
2021	1st Prize for the Best Poster, Leeds Doctoral College Showcase
2021	Professional Development Grant , Society of Spanish Researchers in the UK
2019	Erasmus+ Scholarship, Erasmus+ Programme
2019	Travel Grant from the Spanish Society of Plant Physiology

Publications

(In preparation)	A Gauley, I Lacey, P González-Suárez , D Hirsz, H Taylor, W Harewood, S Griffiths, S Cheng, L Dixon. (In preparation). 'A miRNA-regulated temperature signalling pathway is involved in the regulation of early floral apex development in bread wheat'.
(In review)	P González-Suárez , CH Walker, T Lock, T Bennett. (In preparation). 'FT-mediated thermal signalling regulates age-dependent inflorescence development in Arabidopsis thaliana'.
2023	P González-Suárez , CH Walker, T Bennett. (2023). 'FLOWERING LOCUS T mediates photo-thermal timing of inflorescence meristem arrest in Arabidopsis thaliana'. Plant Physiology 192(3).
2020	K O'Connor [‡] , P González-Suárez [‡] , L Dixon. (2020). 'Temperature Control of Plant Development'. Annual Plant Reviews Online 3(4). [‡] Co-first authors.
2020	P González-Suárez , CH Walker, T Bennett. (2020). 'Bloom and bust: understanding the nature and regulation of the end of flowering'. Current Opinion in Plant Biology 57.
2020	A Ware, CH Walker, J Šimura, P González-Suárez , K Ljung, A Bishopp, Z Wilson, T Bennett. (2020). 'Auxin export from proximal fruits drives arrest in temporally competent inflorescences'. Nature Plants 6.

Talks & Conference Presentations

	•	_	•	
nv	nted	Ser	ทเท	ars

2023	'Environmental Control of the End-of-Flowering in Angiosperms'
	Invited talk, École Normale Supérieure de Lyon, France
2023	'Mathematical Modelling of Cold Sensing in Arabidopsis thaliana'
	Invited talk, University of Glasgow, UK
2022	'Photo-thermal Regulation of the End of Flowering '
	Plantastic Seminars, University of Leeds, UK

Conference Talks

2023	'Rock-a-bye Baby: FLOWERING LOCUS T Coordinates End-of-flowering with
	Offspring Production in Arabidopsis thaliana'
	Iberian Plant Biology 2023 (Braga, Portugal)
2023	'Environmental Regulation of the End of Flowering'
	Faculty of Biological Sciences Postgraduate Researcher Symposium (Leeds, UK)
2022	'The clock is Ticking: FLOWERING LOCUS T as a General Photo-thermal
	Timekeeper for Life-history Transitions'
	32nd International Conference on Arabidopsis Research – ICAR (Belfast, UK)

2021	'Beauty and the Ceased: The key to Never Ending Flowering'
	VIII International Symposium from the Society of Spanish Researchers in the UK
	(Online)
2018	'The study of branching in maritime pine (Pinus pinaster)'
	34th Meeting for Young Researchers (Salamanca, Spain)

Conference Poster Presentations

2023	'Hot and Cold: Mathematical Modeling of Temperature Sensing in Arabidopsis and Wheat'
	Genetics of Future Food Production and the Green Revolution 2.0 (Newcastle, UK)
2022	'The clock is ticking: FLOWERING LOCUS T as a general photo-thermal
	timekeeper for life-history transitions'
	Workshop on Molecular Mechanisms Controlling Flowering (Alicante, Spain)
2021	'Bloom and bust: Why do plants decide when to stop flowering'
	Faculty of Biological Sciences Postgraduate symposium (Online)
2021	'Time to Stop: Photo-thermal Regulation of the End of Flowering'
	31st International Conference on Arabidopsis Research – ICAR (Online)
2021	'Environmental Regulation of Floret Development in Wheat'
	Monogram 2021 (Online)
2021	'Why do plants stop flowering?'
	University of Leeds PGR Showcase Competition (Online)
2020	'Slow it down! Photothermal control of floral arrest in Arabidopsis'
	XV Meeting of Plant Molecular Biology – RBMP (Online)
2020	'Time to stop? Photothermal regulation of end-of-flowering in Arabidopsis'
	Sainsbury Laboratory Symposium – SLS20 (Online)
2019	'Unravelling the mechanisms that control branching in Pinus pinaster: The
	role of strigolactones'
	XXIII Meeting of the Spanish Society of Plant Physiology – FV2019 (Pamplona,
	Spain)

Supervising, Mentoring & Teaching Experience

Supervised Theses

2023	'Genome-Wide Analysis, Phenotypic Characterization, and Gene Expression Profiling of DREB Transcription Factors in Cold Response of <i>S. polyrhiza</i> '
	MSc Thesis, Lateefat Anike Arogundade (Co-supervised with Tom Bennett)
2022	'Understanding the Genetic Basis for Timing of Inflorescence Arrest in
	Arabidopsis thaliana'
	BSc Dissertation, Faye Chesworth (Co-supervised with Tom Bennett)

2022	'Investigation into the Role of FLOWERING LOCUS T in Temperature-signal
	Integration During Reproductive Development in A. thaliana'
	MSc Thesis, Thomas Lock (Co-supervised with Tom Bennett)
2022	'Why Plants Stop Flowering: Identifying the Downstream Targets of
	FLOWERING LOCUS T that Help Regulate Inflorescence Arrest in A. thaliana'
	Mbiol Thesis, Arran Horne (Co-supervised with Tom Bennett)

Current and Past Mentees

2023	Lateefat Anike Arogundade (MSc Erasmus student)
2022	Faye Chesworth (BSc Biology)
2022	Thomas Lock (MSc Plant Science and Biotechnology)
2022	Arran Horne (BSc Biology Mbiol)
2021	Megan Pierce (BSc Biology)
2019	Nuria Álvarez Alija (BSc Biotechnology)
2017	Verónica Fernández González (BSc Teaching)
2017	María del Blanco Blanco (BSc Tourism)
2017	Mario Sabou Pompescu (BSc History)

Other Mentoring & Teaching Experience

2022 Student Mentor in the Reverse Mentoring Project

University of Leeds, United Kingdom

 I took part in this innovative programme that aimed to help senior staff members of the university better understand the specific needs of underrepresented students.

2019 – 2022 Demonstrator

University of Leeds, United Kingdom

• I demonstrated in laboratory practicals from a variety of modules including BLGY2163 ('How Plants Work') and BLGY1234 ('Practical Genetics').

Other Certifications & Courses

2022	Communicating Your Science Workshop, Genetics Society
2022	Data Scientist with R, Datacamp
2020	Mathematics of Life: Modelling Molecular Mechanisms, EMBL-EBI
2020	Foundations in Teaching, University of Leeds
2020	Finding Open Content for your Research, University of Leeds
2019	Advanced Statistics in R, University of Leeds

Memberships

2020 - 2023	Genetics Society
2020 – 2023	Society of Spanish Researchers in the United Kingdom
2019 – 2022	Spanish Society of Plant Physiology (SEFV)